Angola Subject Files, Inclusive: 1975-2004, Bulk: 1976-1993
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Angola Subject Files
Inclusive: 1975-2004, Bulk: 1976-1993
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
3
Keston Institute, 1969 -
2 A4 document boxes
The Angola Subject Files contain a variety of materials related to a range of topics from the Angolan Civil War (1975-2002) to international relations and religious activities.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the name changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist and totalitarian countries. The Keston Archive and Library houses numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals.
Beginning in 1975 and continuing until approximately 2004, Keston collected materials documenting the religious and political climate of Angola. A Portuguese colony, Angola obtained its independence in 1975. The Colonial War, fought for the independence of Angola, lasted from 1961-1974. With Cuban support on November 11, 1975, the Popular Movement for the Liberation of Angola (MPLA) declared independence and established a socialist regime. Agostinho Neto became the first president. Rebel groups from the Colonial War, particularly the National Union for the Total Independence of Angola (UNITA), opposed the socialist regime, and a new civil war broke out lasting from 1975-2002. In 2002, UNITA leader Dr. Jonas Savimbi was killed in combat, and shortly thereafter the government and rebels reached a ceasefire agreement.
With foreign governments assisting both sides, the civil war lasted nearly 30 years. The MPLA received aid from several countries, most notably Cuba and the Soviet Union. Dr. Savimbi and UNITA were supported most prominently by South Africa and the United States. They sent troops, military arms, and medical supplies.
The war raged for nearly a decade before the first signs of an end appeared. The 1980’s brought the prospect of peace talks. Angola, Cuba and South Africa met multiple times and attempted to halt the violence. Discussions centered heavily on the removal of Cuban troops from Angola and the independence of Namibia from South Africa. Finally, after several years and much political maneuvering, the factions reached an agreement. By 1991, South African and Cuban troops had withdrawn from Angola, but the battle with UNITA had not ceased.
As the war continued, Angola became willing to enter into peace talks with the rebel forces partly due to international pressure. The negotiations between Dr. Savimbi and President Jose Eduardo dos Santos finally took place in 1989. With hopes for ending the 14 year old civil war in sight, Dr. Savimbi demanded free elections and received the concession.
In 1992, Angola held its first free, multiparty election overseen by the United Nations. President Jose Eduardo dos Santos and the MPLA won with more than 50% of the vote. Several parties, including Dr. Savimbi, refused to accept the results and proclaimed a rigged election. His response was to continue fighting, and the long anticipated election dashed Angola’s hopes for peace. The civil war continued until Dr. Savimbi’s death in combat in 2002. Shortly thereafter, the two sides agreed to a ceasefire, and the war ended. However partially due to the effects of the civil war, Angola would not hold another free election for 16 years. In 2008, the MPLA party won by an overwhelming majority in the second free, multiparty election.
Scope and Content
Angola subject files consist of newspaper clippings, bibliographic references, correspondence, news releases, and periodicals.
The materials cover the period from 1975 to 2004 with the bulk from 1976 to 1993. The majority of the items pertain to the civil war between the socialist Angolan government and the National Union for the Total Independence of Angola (UNITA), international relations, and religious activity. The main topics of the civil war include, but are not limited to, military actions by rebel forces and the state, peace talks, and the election of 1992. Materials pertaining to Angolan international relations deal mostly with African countries, Cuba, the Soviet Union, and the United States, but other countries are included. The majority of materials pertaining to Angolan religious activity focus on Bible Societies, church activities and growth, missionaries, and oppression.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received the Angola materials organized into two categories, Angola General Files and Angola Religion Files. Within these categories, all materials were organized chronologically. This organization has mostly been preserved but has been broken down further into specific thematic subjects and denominations.
The Angola Files are now arranged into two series: I. General and II. Denominational materials.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Savimbi, Jonas Malheiro.
Subjects (Organizations)
Movimento Popular de Libertação de Angola.; União Nacional para a Independência Total de Angola.
Places
Angola -- Foreign relations -- 1975-; Angola -- History -- Civil War, 1975-2002 -- Participation, Cuban.; Angola -- History -- Civil War, 1975-2002 -- Participation, South African.; Angola -- History -- Civil War, 1975-2002 -- Social aspects.; Angola -- History -- Civil War, 1975-2002.; Angola -- Politics and government -- 1975-
Subjects
Christianity -- Angola.; Cuito Cuanavale, Battle of, Cuito Cuanavale, Angola, 1987-1988.; Elections -- Angola.; Persecution -- Angola.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Periodicals.; Press releases.
- General, 1975-2004; 1
  Administrative Information
  Biography/Profile
  General Angola subject files contain materials pertaining to the Angolan civil war, peace talks, the 1992 election, human rights activity, international relations, communist ideology, refugees, religious persecutions, and other religious activity.
  - General, History, 1976-1993 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - State and Rebel Military Actions, 1976-1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Political Imprisonments, Executions, and Releases, 1980-1987 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dr. Savimbi and the National Union for the Total Independence of Angola (UNITA), 1979-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - UNITA's Abductions, Assaults, and Murder, 1982-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - UNITA's Violence Against Religious Figures, 1980-1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - International Relations, 1977-1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - International Relations with other African Countries, 1977-1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - International Relations with Cuba, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - International Relations with France, 1982-1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - International Relations with Portugal, 1977-1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - International Relations with Soviet Union, 1977-1988 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - International Relations with United Kingdom, 1977-1999 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - International Relations with United States, 1976-1993 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Editorials on Foreign Intervention in Angola, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Angolan Peace Talks with Cuba and South Africa, 1982-1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cuban and South African Military Withdrawals, 1982-1990 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - State and Rebel Peace Talks and Ceasefires, 1983-1993 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Refugees, 1977-2000 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Famine and Casualties of War, 1987-1996 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Government and Law, 1977-1989 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Elections, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Espionage, 1983-1988 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Church and State, 1976-2003 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Constitution, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Communism, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Party Congresses, Decision, etc., 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Purges, 1976-1983 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Economy, 1981-1996 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - General, Interdenominational, 1976-2004 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Ecumenical Movement, 1977-1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Oppressive Practices Relating to Religious Activity, 1976-2003 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Humanitarian Aid from Religious Organizations, 1977-1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bible Societies, 1976-1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Statistics on Religion, 1979-1999 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Denominational, 1976-1999; 2
  Denominational Angola subject files contain categories pertaining to particular denominational activities within Angola.
  - Anglican Church in Angola, 1993-1997 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Baptist Church Activities and Growth, 1976-1999 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Evangelical Church Activities and Growth, 1978-1994 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Lutheran World Information Publications, 1987-1992 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Methodist Church Activities and Growth, 1978-1987 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Methodist Bishop Emilio de Carvalho's Statements, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Roman Catholic Church Activities and Growth, 1976-1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Roman Catholic Bishop Appeals and Diocese, 1976-1999 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Pope John Paul II and His Visit to Angola, 1987-1993 (Box 2, Folder 15)